In the case, In re Prudential Insurance
Company sales practices litigation,
we'll see what factors courts should evaluate
when determining whether a proposed class
action settlement is fair and reasonable.
Eight million Prudential insurance company
policyholders sued Prudential, claiming
that Prudential's sales force engaged in
fraudulent and misleading sales practices.
After all the parties completed extensive
discovery and the policyholders filed
various motions and amended complaints,
the class of policyholders and Prudential
entered into a settlement agreement. The
terms of the settlement agreement proposed a
remediation scheme that allowed class members
to either pursue their claims through an
alternate dispute resolution procedure
known as ADR or elect for basic claim relief.
Under ADR, a class member who believed that he
or she had been misled by Prudential
Salesforce would submit a claim that
would be reviewed in a four tier review process.
The review process included reviews by Prudential
employees and independent evaluators.
Under the basic claim relief, a class
member could obtain relief without
showing Prudential's liability.
The proposed settlement agreement was
not capped by a specific dollar amount.
The district court certified the class and
approved the settlement. Three hundred class
members objected to the settlement, and a
class member appealed the district court's
approval of the settlement agreement to the United
States Court of Appeals for the third circuit.